本片改编自真人真事
尽管角色是真实人物的综合
时间与地点亦经过更改
但是逃亡的细节完全符合事实
下车
Aussteigen.
开门
Tor aufmachen!
进去
Go inside.
赶快
Hurry UP.
走这边
This way.
赶快
Hurry up.
房间还可以 你要哪一张床？
Yeah, this'll do. Which one are you gonna have?
-我… 不行 那是我的
- I... - No, that's mine.
上去
Allez... hup!
丹尼 树林有多远？
How far are the trees, Danny?
至少六十米以上
Over 200 feet.
我看有一百米
Yeah, I'd say 300.
有得挖了
Long ways to dig.
叫卡文迪斯测量一下 真希望大X在这里
We'll get Cavendish to make a survey. I wish Big X were here.
威利 你认为他逃成了吗？
Willie, you think X got away?
如果他逃成了 应该会送消息给我们
He'd have sent us word, somehow, if he had.
-被秘密警察抓了？ -要不然就是死了
- Gestapo, you think? - Either that or he's dead.
-是蓝姆西上校吗？ -我是
- Group Captain Ramsey? - Yes.
我是斯塔赫维兹士官长 请跟我来
I am Hauptfeldwebel Strachwitz. Will you accompany me, please?
-我会照顾你的东西 -好的
- I'll look after your gear, sir. - Right.
蓝姆西上校到了
Gruppenkommandeur Ramsey.
上校 早安
Good morning, Group Captain.
我是鲁格的副官波森上尉
I'm Captain Posen, Von Luger's adjutant.
你是最高阶的英国军官
Since you're senior British officer,
现任你为战俘与上校间的联络人
you are to be liaison between the prisoners and the colonel.
他希望你能明白几件事…
He wishes to make clear to you certain matters of...
正确的词是“政策”吗？
- The word is "policy"? - Yes.
谢谢你
Thank you.
进来
Herein.
这是蓝姆西上校
Gruppenkommandeur Ramsey.
我是鲁格上校 请坐
I am Colonel Von Luger. Please sit down.
蓝姆西上校 四年以来
Group Captain Ramsey, in the past four years
第三帝国不得不花费大量时间
the Reich has been forced to spend an enormous amount of time,
精力 人力与装备
energy, manpower and equipment
追捕脱逃的军官战俘
hunting down escaping prisoner-of-war officers.
至少你们有活干 不是件好事吗？
Hmm. At least it's rather nice to know you're wanted, isn't it?
这不是儿戏 这个战俘营不准逃亡
For us it's not a matter for levity. There will be no escapes from this camp.
鲁格上校 所有军官都宣誓 有责任要试图逃亡
Colonel Von Luger, it is the sworn duty of all officers to try to escape.
如果逃不成 他们也有责任
If they can't, it is their duty to cause the enemy
造成敌人派遣重兵来看守他们
to use an inordinate number of troops to guard them,
他们还宣誓有责任 尽他们的能力扰乱敌人
and their sworn duty to harass the enemy to the best of their ability.
是的 我知道
Yes, I know.
在你麾下的人员是最成功的
The men under your authority have been most successful.
例如这个人 艾希利皮特
This man, Ashley-Pitt, for example.
他在北海被俘 然后逃脱 再度被俘 再逃 再被俘
Caught in the North Sea, escaped, recaptured, escaped, recaptured.
阿奇巴德“阿奇”艾弗斯 11次企图逃脱
Archibald "Archie" Ives, eleven escape attempts.
他甚至企图在卡车来这里的路上跳车
Even tried to jump out of the truck coming here.
狄克斯威廉
Dickes, William.
参与挖掘11条逃亡地道
Known to have participated in digging of 11 escape tunnels.
威林斯基上尉 四次逃脱
Flight Lieutenant Willinski, four escapes.
麦居纳 九次 美国人韩德利 五次
MacDonald, nine. Hendley, the American, five.
海因斯 四次 塞奇威克 七次 名单几乎念不完
Haynes, four. Sedgwick, seven. The list is almost endless.
其中有一个曾经17次企图逃脱
One man here has made 17 attempted escapes.
上校 这近乎疯狂
Group Captain, this is close to insanity.
-差不多了 -这种事必须停止！
- Quite. - And it must stop!
上校 难道你期待军官忘掉他们的责任？
Colonel, do you expect officers to forget their duty?
不是
No.
我们预计你们不会忘记责任 所以才把你们运来这里
It is because we expect the opposite that we have brought you here.
这是新的战俘营
This is a new camp.
是造来关住你和你的部下
It has been built to hold you and your men.
这里集中了我们知道的所有安全设施
It is organized to incorporate all we have learned of security measures.
至于我 你要对付的可不是普通狱卒
And, in me, you will not be dealing with a common jailer,
而是德国空军最高当局亲自挑选的
but with a staff officer personally selected for the task
负责这一任务的参谋军官
by the Luftwaffe high command.
我们把所有的坏蛋都放在一个篮子里
We have, in effect, put all our rotten eggs in one basket,
而且我们要严密看守这个篮子
and we intend to watch this basket carefully.
很聪明
Very wise.
你们可以使用一般的设施
You will not be denied the usual facilities.
运动场 图书馆 休闲厅
Sports, a library, a recreation hall...
我们会给你们园艺的工具
And, for gardening, we will give you tools.
我们信任你们会把工具用在园艺上
We trust you to use them for gardening.
把你们的精力用到这些事情上
Devote your energies to these things.
放弃你们没希望的逃脱企图
Give up your hopeless attempts to escape.
如果你们识时务的话
And, with intelligent cooperation,
我们全都可以舒服地
we may all sit out the war...
等待战争结束
as comfortably as possible.
-你在卡车旁做什么？ -我在偷工具
- What do you do here by the truck? - I'm stealing tools.
-偷工具要关禁闭 -我只是开玩笑
- For stealing tools, cooler. - I was only kidding.
-你是美国人 -我是 你是德国人
- Oh, you're American. - Yes, and you're a German.
当然 你为什么来德国？
Of course. Why do you come to Germany?
-为何为你的敌人英国战斗？ -敌人？你在说什么？
- Why fight for England, your enemy? - Enemy? What are you talkin' about?
-英国在1812年烧了美国首都 -那是宣传
- In 1812 they burned your Capitol. - That's propaganda.
历史书里有 我读过
It's in the history books. I read it.
现在赶快走开 如果你偷工具 就关禁闭
Now go away from here. If you steal tools, cooler.
好 不偷工具
Yeah. No tools.
嘿 维吉
Hey, Virgil.
你有没有看到禁闭室？
Hey, did you see the cooler?
老兄 它可真大！
Boy, is it ever a big one!
-他们预期要关很多人 -大概吧
- I think they expect a lot of business. - Yeah.
我找不到在以前的营地和我们一起住14号房的那两个人
Those two guys who were with us in the old camp, in hut 14, I can't find them.
-卫兵把他们留在那边？ -我猜是的
- You think the goons left 'em behind? - I guess.
他们姓什么？ 一个是杰克森 还有…
What were their names? It was Jackson and, uh...
-德克斯特 -德克斯特 没错
- And Dexter. - Dexter. That's right.
我去看看还能找到谁 待会儿见
I'm gonna see who else I can find. I'll see you later.
丹尼 他们是什么人？
Hey, Danny. Who are they?
俄国战俘 他们是砍树的
Russian prisoners. They cut down trees.
-他们被关在这里吗？ 不 德国人要把他们运走
- They keep them here? - No, they take them out.
威利 香烟
Willie, cigarettes.
丹尼和我要逃走 你们能分散警卫的注意力吗？
Danny and I have a blitz in mind. Could you put on a brief show for the goons?
当然能 你要全体出动吗？
Sure, man. What'll it be? An all-out go?
-要吵闹吗？ -还是要打架？
- Choir practice? - Knuckles, eh?
-好 打架不错 -外套给他
- Yeah. Knuckles will be fine. - Give him the coat.
-你拿我的外套做什么？ -什么？这是我的外套！
- What are you doing with my coat, mate? - What? It's mine!
你敢推我？
Are you pushing me?
那是我的 你这个狗养…
That's mine, you son of a...
(俄语)同志
Товарищ.
(俄语)谢谢
Спасибо.
停止！停止胡闹！
Stop it! Stop this nonsense!
没事 我们只是在善意地争论
It's all right, mate. We're just having a friendly little argument.
不准打架 不准！ -好的
- No more fighting. No more! - All right.
-各自回房 -是的 长官
- Back in your huts. - Yes, sir.
你也回去！
You, too!
走开！回到房间里！
Get away! Get back in your huts!
走啊！
Go on!
希尔兹 看来营地里只有另外一个美国人
Hey, Hilts. Looks like there's only one other American in the whole camp.
参加英国皇家空军老鹰中队 叫韩德利的家伙
Some guy named Hendley in the RAF Eagle squadron.
你已经有计划了吗？
- Hey, you got something goin' already? - Shh!
看到瞭望塔的分布位置吗？
See the way the goons got those towers placed?
中间有一个盲点 -盲点？
- There's a blind spot through the middle. - A blind spot?
站在铁丝网旁边 两个瞭望塔都看不到
A guy could stand at that wire and not be seen by either tower.
尤其是晚上 绝对看不到我
They'd never see me, especially at night.
-你疯了 -是吗？我们马上来证明
- You're crazy. - You think so? Let's find out right now.
下一步稍微困难
Now, the next step's a little tricky.
-你不会出去吧？ -他们瞭望时我不出去
- You're not goin' out there? - Not while they're lookin', I'm not.
我要去散散步
I think I'll take a little walk.
部队行军
Abteilung marsch!
同志
Товарищ.
-丹尼 你会说俄语？ -只会说一句
- Danny, you speak Russian? - Only one sentence.
快教我 -Ja vas lublu
- Let me have it, mate. - Я вас люблю.
-Ja vas -Lublu
- Я вас... - Люблю.
Lublu? Ja vas lublu
Люблю? Я вас люблю.
Ja vas lublu
Я вас люблю.
-是什么意思？ -我爱你
- What's it mean? - I love you.
我爱你？那有什么用？
I love you? What bloody good is that?
我不知道 我自己也不打算用
I don't know. I wasn't going to use it myself.
立正
Halt!
出去
Out.
-出去！-不 不 是同志
- Out! - Nyet, nyet. Товарищ.
你们是朋友吗？-是同志
- Your friend, yes? - Товарищ.
威林斯基上尉 谁来担保你呢？
And who vouches for you, Lieutenant Willinski?
塞奇威克 滚出去
Get out, Sedgwick.
谢谢
Спасибо.
行军
Marsch!
等一下 等一下！
Hold it, hold it!
-你姓什么？ -艾弗斯
- Your name? - Ives.
艾弗斯
Ives. Ives.
艾弗斯 对了 苏格兰人
Oh, yes. Archibald Ives. Scots.
你比相片好看多了
The photograph doesn't do you justice.
看看你们处于类似情况时的模样
I'd like to see one of you under similar circumstances.
我现在不采取行动
I will not take action against you now.
这是第一天 出现了很多愚蠢和大意的事
This is the first day here, and there has been much stupidity and carelessness...
双方都有
on both sides.
嘿！回来！
' Hey! Get out!
不要开枪！
Nicht schieBen! Nicht schieBen!
Don't shoot!
笨蛋！越线就死定了！
You fool! To cross the wire is death!
-什么线？ -这条线！警告线！
- What wire? - This wire! The warning wire!
是吗
Oh.
绝对不准越过这条线 你是知道的
It's absolutely forbidden to cross it. You know that.
我的棒球滚到那边去了 该怎样拿回来？
But my baseball rolled over there. How am I gonna get my baseball?
-你应该先请求准许 -好吧
- You first ask permission. - Oh, OK.
-我要捡棒球 -停止！立刻回到线这边！
Gettin' my baseball. - Stop this! Get over the wire immediately!
-好 -站住别动！
- OK. - You stay there!
让路 让路
Out of the way. Out.
你在铁丝网旁边做什么？
What are you doing over here by the wire?
我跟麦克斯说过 我要捡…
Like I told Max, I was trying to get my...
-你在铁丝网旁边做什么？ -我跟麦克斯说过…
- What were you doing by the wire? - Well, like I told Max...
我想逃出去 所以试图剪断铁丝网
I was trying to cut my way through your wire, because I wanna get out.
搜他的身
Durchsuchen Sie ihn.
你会说德语吗？-是的上校
- Do you speak German? - Jawohl, Herr Oberst.
剪线器？-是的上校
- Wire cutters. - Jawohl, Herr Oberst.
我很高兴在这场战争中认识好几位英国军官
I have had the pleasure of knowing quite a number of British officers in this war.
让我感到高兴的是 双方互相理解
And I flatter myself that we understand one another.
希尔兹  你是我遇到的首位美国军官 对吗？
You are the first American officer I have met. Hilts, isn't it?
请叫我希尔兹上尉
Captain Hilts, actually.
-17次企图逃脱 -是18次
- Seventeen escape attempts. - Eighteen, sir.
-地道专家 工程师 -飞行员
- Tunnel man, engineer. - Flier.
我猜就是美国军方说的红牌飞行员
I suppose what's called in the American army a "hotshot pilot."
不幸的是 你被击落了
Unfortunately, you were shot down anyway.
战争期间你我都停飞了
So we are both grounded for the duration of the war.
上校 你说的是你自己
Well, you speak for yourself, Colonel.
-你有别的计划？ -我还没从空中或地上看过柏林
- You have other plans? - I haven't seen Berlin yet.
我计划在战争结束以前去看看
I plan on doing so before the war's over.
美国军官都像你这样没礼貌？
Are all American officers so ill-mannered?
大约九成九是这样
About 99 percent.
或许和我们一起的时候 你可以学一点礼貌
Perhaps while you are with us, you will have a chance to learn some.
希尔兹 关禁闭十天
Ten days isolation, Hilts.
叫我希尔兹上尉 -关20天
- Captain Hilts. - Twenty days.
关就关
Right.
我出来的时候 你还会在这里吗？
Oh, you'll still be here when I get out?
禁闭室
Cooler.
-姓氏？ -艾弗斯
- Name? - Ives.
艾弗斯中尉
Flying Officer Ives.
禁闭20天
Cooler, 20 days.
艾弗斯 去禁闭室 -是我的荣幸
- Cooler, Ives. - Pleasure.
-希尔兹 -什么事？
- Hilts. - Yeah?
你在美国做什么？打棒球吗？
What did you do in the States? Play baseball?
不是 我是大学生
No, I was in college.
-艾弗斯 -什么事？
- Say, Ives. - Aye?
-你试过几次逃脱？ -地面四次 地下七次
- How many escapes have you tried? - Four over, seven under.
-地道专家 是吗？ -不敢当
- Tunnel man, huh? - Sure, I am that.
艾弗斯 你有多高？
How tall are you, Ives?
162公分 干嘛？
Five feet four. Why?
只是问问
Oh, just wondering.
你在大学念什么？学体育吗？
What did you do in college? Study physical education?
学化工 但是爱骑车
Chemical engineering. Did a little bike riding, though.
骑脚踏车？
- Bicycles? - Motorcycles.
骑摩托车 赛车 表演会 到处赚一点小钱
Flat tracks, county fairs. Picked up a buck here and there.
-帮助缴学费 -我也参加过比赛
- Helped pay my tuition. - I did a wee bit of racing myself.
-在苏格兰 -摩托车？
- In Scotland. - Bikes?
不 是赛马 我是骑师
No, horse racing. Jockey.
骑师
Jockey.
希尔兹？
Hilts?
希尔兹 你还在听吗？
Are you there, Hilts?
我在听
Yeah, I'm here.
难道美国没有骑师吗？
Don't you have them in the States? Jockeys?
当然有
- Sure. - They were the days.
那些日子真好 在马瑟堡和汉弥顿的周六夜
Saturday nights in towns like Musselburgh and Hamilton.
妞儿直往你身上挤
You had to fight off the birds.
知道吗 妞儿耶
You know, birds.
女孩子 老兄 就是女孩子
Girls, man. Girls.
难道美国没有女孩子吗？
Do you not have them in the States?
希尔兹？
Hilts? Are you there, Hilts?
希尔兹 你还在听吗？
艾弗斯
Ives.
什么事？
What?
你懂得营地里的黏土和碎石吗？
You know the kind of clay and gravel we got here in the compound?
你认为八小时之内能够挖多少尺？
How many feet do you think you could get through in eight hours?
我可以像钻头一样轻易挖穿这里的土
I could go through this dirt here like the bit on an end of an auger.
但是挖土并不难 用木头支撑地道
But you know it's not the digging. It's the shoring up with wood,
还要把土运出来 那才是难题
and getting the dirt out, that's what you've to worry about.
不 艾弗斯 你不需要担心
No, it isn't, Ives. You don't have to worry about that.
你怎么把土运出来呢？
How are you going to get the dirt out?
你们在苏格兰怎么称呼地鼠？ -就叫地鼠
- What do they call a mole in Scotland? - A mole.
原来如此
Aye.
你认为怎样？
Well, what do you think?
最初20分钟很有意思
I must say, it's an interesting first 20 minutes.
我认为我们出了洋相
I'd say we made fools of ourselves.
就像那个士官说的 这只是第一天
As the sergeant out there says, this is only the first day.
艾利克
Eric.
不要引起太多注意 警卫可能不知道他是谁
Don't take too much notice. The goons may not know who he is.
-我去传话 -我去告诉老头子
- I'll pass the word. - I'll tell the old man.
他到了
He has arrived.
鲁格上校 战俘巴特利交给你看管
The prisoner Bartlett is discharged into your custody, Colonel Von Luger.
我建议把这个战俘
I suggest this prisoner be kept
永久关在警卫最严密的地方
under the strictest security confinement permanently.
记录库恩先生的建议
Make a note of Herr Kuhn's suggestion.
我们有理由相信
We have reason to believe he is the leader
他是多次脱逃企图的领导人
of numerous criminal escape attempts.
你们看管了巴特利三个月
Squadron Leader Bartlett has been three months in your care,
但是秘密警察只是“有理由相信”吗？
and the Gestapo has only "reason to believe"?
如果他再次落入我们手里 就不会这么幸运了
If he once more falls into our hands, he will not be so lucky.
空军军官战俘是由德国空军看管
Air-force officer prisoners are the responsibility of the Luftwaffe,
不是由党军看管
not the SS...
也不是由秘密警察看管
or the Gestapo.
上校先生 目前是这样
At present, yes, Herr Oberst.
所以他暂时归你看管
That is why he is returned, for the moment, to your care.
当然 如果空军没有能力
Of course, if the Luftwaffe is not up to the task,
就由我们全权处置战俘
the prisoners will find themselves totally in our charge.
我们就不是那么体谅
We regretfully are not so professionally understanding.
巴特利少校
Squadron Leader Bartlett,
如果你再次逃脱被抓到 就会被枪毙
if you escape again and be caught, you will be shot.
希特勒万岁 -希特勒万岁
- Heil Hitler. - Heil Hitler.
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler.
库恩先生
Herr Kuhn.
拿掉他的东西
ehmen Sie dem Mann diese Dinger ab.
-艾利克 -你好 罗杰
- Eric. - Hello, Roger.
-他们把你也扔到这里来了 -这里情况如何？
- They dumped you here, too. - What's this one like?
这里是新的战俘营
Well, it's new.
-给你找一个床位 -谢谢
- Here. Let's find you a bed. - Thanks.
请进
Come in.
-你好 罗杰 -你好 长官
- Hello, Roger. - Hello, sir.
-我把行李放在你房里 -艾利克 谢谢
- I'll put your bag in your room. - Thanks, Eric.
-你好吗？ -马马虎虎
- How are you? - As well as can be expected.
弟兄们想为你办欢迎会 但是稍后再谈
The fellows wanted to put up a welcome committee, but that's for later.
-我看到威利 威林斯基和麦克 -这里有很多老朋友
- I saw Willie and Willinski with Mac. - A lot of old friends here.
-你来这里多久了？ -今天来的
- How long have you been here, sir? - Arrived today.
新营地 优秀的警卫 精英
New camp, expert guards, the elite.
你见过指挥官吗？
You met the commandant?
我见过
Yes, I did.
秘密警察和党军找你有什么事？
What were the Gestapo and the SS doing with you?
他们想知道谁帮助我抵达边界
They wanted to find out who helped me to the border.
-这里还有谁？有卡文迪斯吗？ -有的
- Who else is here? Cavendish? - Mm-hm.
-尼莫和索伦呢？ -葛里菲斯 海因斯
- Nimmo and Sorren? - Griffith, Haynes.
-布莱斯呢？ -有的
- Blythe? - Yes.
几乎整个X组织都在
Almost the whole X organization.
差不多
Almost.
德国人清理所有的营地 把我们都扔在这里
They cleaned out all the other camps and dumped us in this one.
就像鲁格说的： 所有的坏蛋都在一个篮子里
As Von Luger put it, "All the rotten eggs in one basket."
他们的方法有点疯狂
There's madness in their method.
汤米布里斯托呢？
- What about Tommy Bristol?
不在 但是有美国人韩德利
No, but there's an American, Hendley.
他擅长敲诈吗？
Is he a scrounger, blackmailer?
-麦居纳说他是最行的 -好
- MacDonald says he's the best. - Good.
在红十字物资再来以前 这是最后的茶了
Last of the tea until the Red Cross gets through again.
我从塞奇威克敲来的
I scrounged this from Sedgwick.
秘密警察有没有让你受罪？
Did the Gestapo give you a rough time?
没有我想要他们受的多
Not nearly as rough as I now intend to give them.
罗杰 个人恩怨不能和 我们要做的事混为一谈
Roger, personal revenge must be kept out of what we have to do here.
攸关的人命太多了
Too many lives are at stake.
我个人的感觉并不重要
What my personal feelings are is of no importance.
你派我领导X组织
You appointed me Big X, and it's my duty to harass,
我的责任是尽力扰乱 困惑与混淆敌人
confound and confuse the enemy to the best of my ability.
-没错 -那就是我要做的事
- That's true. - That's what I intend to do.
我要在他们的帝国里制造极大的麻烦
I'm gonna cause such a terrible stink in this Third Reich of theirs
牵制好几千部队来寻找我们
that thousands of troops'll be tied up here looking after us.
怎么做呢？
How?
派出更多的人…
By putting more men out of this...
逃出他们自认为完美的战俘营
perfect camp of theirs than have ever escaped before.
不是二三十人 而是二三百人 让他们散布到德国各地
Not two or three or a dozen, but 200, 300. Scatter them all over Germany.
-能做到吗？ -这里人才济济
- Think that's possible? - The men are hereto do it.
你自己说的  他们把全德国每个逃脱专家都关在这里
The goons have put every escape artist in Germany here. You said so yourself.
你想过可能的代价？
Have you thought of what it might cost?
我想过如果我们就此温顺屈服
I've thought of the humiliation if we just tamely submit,
对他们卑身屈膝
knuckle under and crawl.
长官 你当然不提倡屈服吧？
Surely you don't advocate that, do you, sir?
罗杰 我必须指出一件事
I have to point out one thing to you, Roger.
不论这个营地多糟
No matter how unsatisfactory this camp may be,
德军高层仍然让德国空军 来看管我们
the high command have left us in the hands of the Luftwaffe,
不是秘密警察与党军
not the Gestapo and the SS.
长官 你提到德国空军高层
Look, sir, you talk about the high command of the Luftwaffe,
还有党军与秘密警察
then the SS and the Gestapo.
我认为他们都是一样的 我们要对抗他们全体
To me they're the same. We're fighting the bloody lot.
一言概之
There's only one way to put it, sir.
他们是每个信仰自由的人的公敌
They are the common enemies of everyone who believes in freedom.
如果他们不认同希特勒 为什么不推翻他？
If they didn't approve of Hitler, why didn't they throw him out?
罗杰 我不与你争议
I have no argument with you, Roger.
身为高阶军官 我只是指出有关的事实
As senior officer, I'm merely pointing out a pertinent fact.
X 你什么时候召开会议？
When are you calling a meeting, X?
今天晚上
Tonight.
各位 你们无疑都听过新指挥官的不朽名言
Gentlemen, no doubt you've heard the immortal words of our new commandant.
“把你们的精力用在 逃脱之外的事情上”
"Devote your energies to things other than escape,
舒服地等待战争结束
and sit out the war as comfortably as possible."
那就是我们要做的
Well, that's exactly what we're going to do.
我们要把精力用在运动与园艺
We're going to devote our energies to sports and gardening,
还有他们认同的种种文化活动
all the cultural pursuits as far as they're concerned.
让他们放松警戒
In fact, we're going to put the goons to sleep.
同时…我们也要挖地道
Meanwhile... we dig.
只要稍微观察一下营地
Now, even a superficial look at the compound
就会发现104号与105号营房 最接近树林
shows us that huts 104 and five are closest to the woods.
第一条地道从105出发
The first tunnel goes out from 105,
向东穿过禁闭室与铁丝网底下
directly east under the cooler and the wire.
罗杰 那有九十多米
But that's over 300 feet, Roger.
-丹尼斯 你测量过吗？ -只是初步测量
- Did you make a survey, Dennis? - Only a temporary one, sir.
-估计有一百多米 -有精确数字再告诉我
- I make it just over 335 feet. - Tell me when you've got an exact one.
威利 我们这次向下挖十米 然后再转水平方向
Willie, this time we'll dig straight down 30 feet before we go horizontal.
那就可以消除声响或者探针的探测
That'll rule out any question of sound detection or probing.
好的 罗杰 但是… 你是不是说第一条地道？
All right, Roger, but... did you say the first tunnel?
是的 总共有三条
I did. There'll be three.
我们叫它们汤姆 狄克与哈利 汤姆从104直接向东
We'll call them Tom, Dick and Harry. Tom goes out directly east from 104.
狄克从厨房向北 哈利从105出发与汤姆平行
Dick goes north from the kitchen, and Harry goes out parallel to Tom from 105.
如果警卫发现一条地道 我们就转移到另一条
If the goons find one, we'll move into the other.
罗杰 你计划带多少人出去？
How many men do you plan to take out, Roger?
250人
Two hundred and fifty.
这一次要有充份准备 人人都要有身份证件
There'll be no half measures this time. Identification papers for everyone.
葛里夫 我们需要服装
And, Griff, we'll need outfits for the lot.
-250个人的？ 大部份是平民便服
- Two hundred and fifty? - Mostly civilian clothes.
但是…
Yes, but, uh...
罗杰 好的
OK, Roger.
麦克 从步的人要有地图 毯子 口粮 罗盘
Mac. Maps, blankets, rations, compasses for all the walkers.
-每班火车的时刻表 -好的 罗杰
- Timetables for every train. - Right, Roger.
-抱歉 我迟到了 -柯林 没关系 请坐
- Sorry I'm late, Roger. - It's all right, Colin. Sit down.
我们要挖地道
- We're going to tunnel. -
好极了
Splendid.
威利和丹尼负责地道 丹尼负责设立活门
Willie, you and Danny'll be tunnel kings. Danny, in charge of traps.
塞奇威克制造工具 葛里夫做裁缝
Sedgwick, manufacturer. Griff, as I said, tailor.
尼莫和海因斯分散警卫注意力 麦克当然是负责情报
Nimmo and Haynes, diversions. Mac, of course, will take care of intelligence.
韩德利 幸会
Hendley. We haven't met.
-敲诈专家？ -是的
- Scrounger? - Right.
丹尼斯负责地图和测量
Dennis, maps and surveys.
柯林的任务与以前一样
Colin, you'll take your usual job.
艾利克 你要怎样解决废土？
Eric, how are you gonna get rid of this dirt?
老地方 我没想到有三条地道 但是事在人为
Usual places. I hadn't anticipated three tunnels, but we'll manage.
罗杰 谁负责保密？
Roger, who's going to handle security for all this?
你负责 我需要监视系统 前后兼顾
You are. I want a system of stooges covering this compound
涵盖整个营区 跟踪每个警卫的动静
from front to back, checking every goon in and out.
我需要完美的信号系统
I want a signal system so perfect that
如果警卫走近工作营房15米内
if ever a ferret gets within 50 feet of any of the huts in which we're working,
我们就能无声无息停止工作
we can shut down without a sign.
今晚讨论到此为止
Well, I don't think there's much point in discussing any more now.
我与各位在运动场见面 敲定细节
I'll meet each of you on the exercise circuit, we'll pound out the details.
没别的事了 麦克？
- Nothing else, is there, Mac?
没有了
I shouldn't think so, Roger.
你好
Oh, hello.
我是布莱斯
My name's Blythe.
我是韩德利
Hendley.
-看鸟用的 -我以前也打猎
- For birds. - I used to do a little hunting myself.
不是打猎 是观赏
Oh, not hunting. Watching.
是…赏鸟者？
Oh, a... bird watcher?
是的 赏鸟与画鸟
Yes, that's right. Watching them and drawing them.
美国应该也有赏鸟者？
I suppose you have bird watchers in the States?
有一些
Yes, we have some.
喝茶吗？
Tea?
我只在住院时喝过一次茶
I only drank tea once, in the hospital.
你的东西在哪里？
- Where's your kit? - This is it.
就这些 其他的 在上次大检查时被没收了
The rest was confiscated in the last shakedown.
警卫不喜欢我的某些… 个人物品
The goons didn't appreciate some of my more... personal items.
比如说这个
Such as.
你是敲诈专家 -是的
- You're the scrounger. - Yes, that's right.
我需要一架照相机
I'll need a camera.
什么类型？ -好用的
- What kind? - A good one.
35毫米镜头 2.8焦距 和焦平面快门就可以了
A 35mm f2.8 with a focal-plane shutter should do all right.
好的
All right.
-还要胶卷 -当然
- And film, of course. - Oh, of course.
韩德利 我需要大型尖嘴锄
Oh, Hendley. I need a pick. Big heavy one.
-只要一个？ -两个更好
- Only one? - Two would be better.
这杯茶恐怕淡得很
I'm afraid this tea's pathetic.
这些烂茶叶 我一定泡过大约二十次了
I must have used these wretched leaves about 20 times.
不是我过份挑别
It's not that I mind so much.
但是没有牛奶的茶太不文明了
Tea without milk is so uncivilized.
我去找木头
Yeah. I'll get our wood.
关窗！关窗！
Close up! Close up!
关窗！
Close up!
-听不懂 请说英语 -关窗！
- No me sprechen the English. - Close up!
太好了
Oh. Splendid.
布莱斯 你在这里做什么？
- Blythe, what are you doing here? - Hmm? Oh.
我在解读空中祯照的单位
I'm in Photographic Aerial Reconnaissance Interpretation.
顺便开飞机亲自去看看 都是我不好
Went for a joyride to see for myself. It's my own silly fault.
飞机被打中击落了 真可怕
The aircraft bought it. Got shot down. Terrifying.
不 我是说在营里做什么？ 一战俘营里？
- No, I mean, what do you do here? - Here?
我是伪造专家
I'm the forger.
伪造专家都在休闲厅里
Forgers are installing themselves in the recreation hut.
-塞奇威克呢？ -我在110号营房
- Sedgwick? - I'm in 110.
-葛里菲斯 -我想在109号工作
- Griffith. - Well, I'd like to work in 109, Roger.
109？好的
- 109? Right. - I'll work in 107.
我在107 丹尼 威利和活门队员在104
For now, Danny, Willie and their trap team will be in 104.
麦克 我想在地道方面冒险 不用支撑就向前挖掘
I want to take a chance on the tunnels and press ahead without any shoring-up.
我们需要木材支撑竖坑和进出室
We will need timber for the shafts and the entrance chambers.
韩德利算过有36个空床位
Hendley figures there are 36 empty bunks.
我们折拌15个 然后调动人员 以免被警卫发觉
We can tear up 15 and move the men around so the goons won't miss them.
其他的木材要靠折墙板
The rest will come from strips off the wall.
-韩德利在亲自处理吗？ -还没有
Is Hendley taking care of this himself? - Not yet.
他正在设法帮丹尼弄到 尖嘴锄的钢材
He's working on some steel for a pick that Danny needs.
这里在搞什么鬼？
Hey! What the hell is going on here?
把水关掉！把手拿开！
Turn the water off! Get your hands away!
滚开！
Get away!
嘿！这里在搞什么鬼？
Hey! What the hell's going on there?
停止胡闹！
Stop this nonsense!
滚开！
Get away!
把水关掉！
Turn the water off!
滚开！
Somewhere!
我们让炉子一直燃烧 警卫就不会发觉炉子被搬开了
In the stove, we keep fire burning, always. The goons will not feel like moving it.
韩德利 两块磁砖砍了 我们需要新的
- Good. - Hendley, two tiles, they are chipped. We need new ones.
113的盘洗室里有一些 应该会天衣无缝
- There's some in 113's washroom. - Should match perfectly. - Good.
丹尼 这件事有点难度
It's going to be a bit tricky, Danny.
麦克 有组织就不难
Not when you're organized, Mac.
-我们准备好了 -够大吗？
- We're ready. - Big enough?
好极了 正好穿过地基的中央
It's perfect. Right through the middle of the foundation.
丹尼 祝我们好运
Good luck to us, Danny.
为什么写17 ?
Why 17?
这是丹尼开挖的第17条地道
This is the 17th tunnel Danny's started.
没事吧？
All right?
情况还可以
It's good.
很好
It's very good.
出去！
- Get out! - Raus hier!
怎么不在你的营房里？ 你在这里做什么？
You're not in your hut? What are you doing here?
拖地
Mopping UP-
-你呢？ -淋浴 我需要洗澡
- And you? - Shower. I need a wash.
我在照顾他 我是救生员
I'm watching him. I'm a lifeguard.
穿上保暖的衣服 你可能整晚都在外面罚站
Put on warm clothes. You might be outside all night.
我反对 我们已经完全照你说的让警卫松懈
No. I vote no. Look, we've put the goons to sleep exactly like you said.
但是这样的小问题 足以使我们陷入困境
But just one little thing like this and we're up the creek without a paddle.
-艾弗斯 坐下 -你好 长官
- Ives, sit down, won't you? - Hello, sir.
这是巴特利少校 希尔兹上尉
Hello. Squadron Leader Bartlett, Captain Hilts.
麦唐纳上尉
Flight Lieutenant MacDonald.
我听说你们俩个想逃出去
I understand you two are contemplating a blitz-out.
长官…你从哪里听说的？
Where'd you hear that... sir?
麦居纳说的 他有责任知道每一件事
MacDonald. It's Mac's job to know everything that goes on.
我们想好好谈一谈
We thought, perhaps, we might talk it over.
为什么？这只是两个人的事
Why? It's only a two-man job.
营里每个人都应该事先向巴特利少校
Everybody in the camp is supposed to clear all escape attempts in advance
申请获准逃脱的企图
with Squadron Leader Bartlett here.
我们不想干扰你们
We don't necessarily want to interfere.
只不过… 你们计划怎样逃脱？
It's just that... Well, what sort of blitz were you contemplating?
我们晚上溜出去 到铁丝网旁边我发现的盲点
We sneak out at night to a spot I found near the wire, a blind spot.
然后我们向下挖一米 把土散开以免堆起来
Then we dig down, take the dirt, spread it on top so it won't make a pile,
然后一直挖出去
and then straight out.
艾弗斯是地道专家 他在前面挖 把土推到后面
Ives here is a tunnel man, so he digs in front, pushes the dirt behind him.
我把土推到后面 然后我们 像两只地鼠一样钻过泥土
I stash it behind me, then we burrow through the dirt like a couple of moles.
天亮时 我们从铁丝网底下 越过空地 进入树林逃走
By dawn we're under the wire, across the open space, into the woods and gone.
这个嘛…
Well, uh...
你打算何时试看看？
- When do you intend to try this? - Hmm?
-你打算何时试看看？ -就在今晚
- When do you intend to try it? - Oh, tonight.
希尔兹 现在可能不是 做这种事的适当时机
Hilts, this may not be quite the right time for this sort of thing.
长官 我被关已经快三年了
Look, sir, I've been in the bag nearly three years now,
我快要疯了
bloody close to being wire-happy.
我要逃出去 其他免谈
It's a blitz-out for me, or forget it.
会成功的 我知道会成功的
It'll Work. I know it Will.
祝你好运
Good luck.
谢谢你
Thank you.
-希尔兹 你们怎么呼吸？ -我们有一根附铰链的钢棒
- Hilts, um... how do you breathe? - We got a steel rod with hinges on it.
前进时 把它向上推 戳出通气孔
We shove it up and make air holes as we go along.
长官 晚安
Good night, sir.
为什么以前没人想到那一招？
Now, why didn't anybody think of that before?
这真是简单到了高明之至
It's so stupid, it's positively brilliant.
但是会使营地里 每个警卫紧盯我们
But it'll bring every goon in the camp down on top of us.
不一定 或许我们聪明过头了
I don't know. Perhaps we're being too clever.
如果我们阻止所有的逃脱
If we stop all the breakouts,
警卫反而会认定 我们在挖地道
it may only convince the goons that we must be tunneling.
我希望他们成功 否则 他们会在禁闭室呆很久
I hope it works. If it doesn't, they're going to be in the cooler for an awful long time.
-好吗？ -丹尼 这美极了
- Good, huh? - Danny, it's bloody beautiful.
-这是营地里的土 -这是地道里的土
This is the dirt from the compound. - This is from the tunnel.
不论把土放在哪里 他们大老远就能看见
Wherever we put it, they're going to spot it a mile away.
或许可以放在营房底下 那里的土色比较深
Maybe we could put it under the huts. The dirt's dark there.
那是警卫首个检查的地方 我昨天看到他们在测量
It's the first place the ferrets'd look. I saw one measuring yesterday.
或许可以烘干到同样颜色
Maybe we could dry it to the same color.
-但是有50吨的土 -我只是想到什么就说什么
- There are 50 tons of it. - I was just thinking out loud.
如果你要思考 就想清楚一点
If you must think, for God's sake, think clearly.
艾希利皮特在哪里？
Where the devil is Ashley-Pitt?
我们无法摧毁 吃掉废土
We can't destroy the dirt and we can't eat it.
唯一的方法就是梅饰
The only thing left to do is camouflage it.
我只能想到这么多
That's as far as my thinking takes me.
皇家海军没有教你要迅速吗？
Didn't they teach you promptness in the RN?
你们绝对不会相信 但是我有解决的方法了
You'll never believe it, but I think I have the solution.
我们要想办法 把地道废土散布到营地各处
The problem is somehow to get rid of this tunnel dirt over the compound.
当然是的
Well, of course.
请让一下好吗？
Would you mind?
现在…
Now...
将地道的废土装满这些袋子
you fill these bags with the dirt from the tunnel.
然后把袋子穿在长裤里面
Then, wearing them inside your trousers,
你在营地里闲进
you wander out into the compound
拉动裤袋里的绳子
where you pull these strings in your pockets.
废土就会掉下来
Out come the pins.
-艾利克 好办法 -你只要用脚混合泥土
- Eric, it's good. - All you have to do is kick it in.
除非你是傻瓜 否则警卫不会看到的
Unless you're a fool, the ferrets won't see a thing.
这真是鬼聪明 罗杰 你认为好不好？
It's indecently brilliant. What do you think, Roger?
-明天一早试试看 -我已经试过了 而且成功了
- We'll try it first thing tomorrow. - I already have. it works.
麦克 我们要林取这些行动
Mac, this is what we'll do.
-汤姆送的小礼物 -谢谢你
- A little present from Tom, sir. - Thank you, Nimmo.
长官 菜园真不错
Nice garden you've got, sir.
注意 好好表现一下
All right. Let's look sharp.
表现得很好
That looks sharp.
长官
Sir.
各位先生 请继绩 这只是例行检查
Please, gentlemen, continue. This is merely a routine inspection.
-上校 -长官 早安  早安
- Good morning, Squadron Leader. - Good morning, sir.
很抱歉这里的土坏不适合种植
I am sorry the soil here isn't better suited to your men's purpose.
我们能应付
We'll manage, sir.
上校 我对园艺的规模大感意外
I must say I am surprised with the extent of this activity, Group Captain.
-既高兴又惊奇 -怎么会惊奇？
- Pleased, of course, but surprised. - Surprised, Colonel?
飞行员是绅士 不是农人 居然在挖土
Fliers are gentlemen, not peasants to dig in the earth. So I am surprised.
英国人一向热爱田艺
- The English are keen on gardening. - Oh, yes, but flowers. Is this not so?
但那是说种花 不是吗？
花不能吃
You can't eat flowers, Colonel.
有道理
Good point.
我有不祥之感 他好像完全知道我们在做什么
I have the nasty feeling he knows exactly what we're doing.
-也许吧 不是真的吧？
- Maybe he does. - You don't really think so, do you?
很快就会知道谜底了
If he does, we'll find out soon enough.
-鲍伯 早安 -安迪
- Morning, Bob. - Andy.
东西到了 我们清点一下
Here we are. Now, let's see.
两包饼干
Biscuits, two packets.
两罐咖啡
Coffee, two tins.
一瓶牛肉汁
Bovril, one jar.
六包香烟
Cigarettes, six packets.
索伦的草毒医 卡文迪斯的黑醋东医
Strawberry jam, Sorren's. Blackcurrant jam, Cavendish.
还有我的橘子医
And marmalade, mine.
鲁格的丹麦奶油 我从他的补给品收复来的
Danish butter, Von Luger's. I liberated it from his mess supplies.
唤 还有两条荷兰巧克力
Oh, yes. And Dutch chocolate. Two bars.
整个组织的食物礼品 都捐出来了
That cleans out the gift food for the entire organization.
我们需要的第一样东西 就是新式通行证
Now, the first thing we need is the new form of travel permit.
伪造专家从未见过新式通行证
The forgers have no idea what it looks like.
我来想想办法
I'll see what I can do.
还要其他你能弄到手的身份证
And, of course, any other identity cards, personal papers,
个人证件和文件
documents you can put your hands on.
-好好利用它们 -是的
- Anyway, put 'em to work, Bob. - Right.
祝好运
Good luck.
信神的人们来吧
O come all ye faithful
欢欣又鼓舞
Joyful and triumphant
大家来吧
O come ye
来到伯利怔
O come ye to Bethlehem
来见证它
Come and behold Him
天使之王的诞生
Born the King of Angels
我们来崇敬它
O come let us adore Him
路易 鼓风机在什么鬼地方？
Louis, where the hell is the air pump?
耐心是一种美德
Patience is a virtue, Roger.
我知道 但是只有打开活门 挖地道的人才能工作
Yes, I know, but the diggers can only work when the trap's open,
这严重阻碍了进程
and this is holding us up very badly.
-鼓风机完成了吗？ -当然
- Is it finished? - Of course.
-为什么没装进去？ -因为正在制造通风管
- Why isn't it in? - Working on the air ducts now.
-通风管何时完工？ －一 两天
- Well, when will they be finished? - One or two days.
-有效吗? -当然有效
- Does it work? - Of course it works.
-能提供足够的空气吗？ -绰绰有余
- Will it give us enough air? - As much as you'll need.
麦克
Mac.
好极了
Excellent.
明天晚上以前装进去
Have it in by tomorrow night.
-有火吗？ -有
- Got a light? - Yeah.
多谢
Thanks.
-真不赖 是吗？ -是不赖
- It's pretty, isn't it? - Yes.
抱歉 你要一根吗？
Oh, I'm sorry. Would you like one?
我下岗后再抽 谢谢
I'll smoke it later, when I'm off duty. Thank you.
你或许有两个室友
You probably have a couple of roommates, huh?
-好天气 -是啊 可能会下雨
- Beautiful day. - Yes, but I think it might rain later.
不会 不会
No, no.
早晨的天空发红 水手就紧张
Red sky in the morning, sailor takes warning.
晚上的天空发红 水手就高兴
Red sky at night, sailor's delight.
昨晚的天空是红的
It was a red sky last night.
我从没听说过
I never heard that before.
我在童子军学的
I learned it in the Boy Scouts.
-你以前是童子军？我也是 -真的？
- You were a Boy Scout? So was I. - Really?
-是啊 我有19个奖章 -我有20个
- Yes. I had 19 merit badges. - I had 20.
我正在争取第20个时 政府废除了童军制度
I was working on my 20th when the government abolished scouting
并把我送进希特勒青年团
and sent me into the Hitler Youth instead.
韦纳 战后你会留在军队里吗？
Werner, you think you'll stay in the army after the war?
不会 我身体不好
No. I'm not a well man.
-我的牙齿… -你的牙齿？
- And my teeth... - Your teeth?
对了 关于我牙齿的故事
Yes. I could tell you stories about my teeth
会让你毛骨悚然
that would make your hair stand on end.
这里的牙医是屠夫
Our dentist here is a butcher.
不要告诉别人我这么说
But don't tell anyone I said so.
军人有抱怨的权利
- It's a soldier's right to complain.
也许你的军队就行 这里嘛？
Maybe in your army, but here?
提出一点批评 就被送到…俄国前线
One little criticism, and... to the Russian front.
是这样吗？真可怕
Is that so? Terrible.
那太可怕了
That's terrible.
韦纳
Werner.
到我房间去谈好吗？舒服些
Why don't we go into my room?
最好不要 如果斯塔赫维兹看见…
I'd better not. If Strachwitz should see me...
我只是要泡咖啡
I was just gonna make some coffee.
真正的咖啡
Real coffee.
咖啡
Coffee, coffee, coffee.
咖啡在哪里？
Where is it?
果酱 真好
Marmelade. Ist ja wunderbar.
我祖母老是寄这种东西给我
My grandmother keeps sending me this stuff.
天哪 巧克力
- Ach du lieber Gott, Schokolade.
来 拿一个
Oh, yeah. Here. Take one.
鲁格的奶油
- Von Lugers Butter.
是啊 收下吧
Yeah. Keep it.
不行 我该走了
Nein. I must go.
没关系 拿去吧 我们是朋友
It's OK. You can keep it. We're friends.
你关禁闭 我们还是朋友？ 我必须报告这件事
With you in the cooler, will we be friends? I must report this.
报告什么？ 说你和我在我的房间聊天？
I don't understand you. Report what? That you and I were chatting in my room?
-我必须走了 -拿着 没问题的
- I must go. - Oh, here. It's OK. Look, keep it.
我反正吃不了这么多
- I'll never be able to eat it all. - Nein, ich muss jetzt weg.
对不起 算了
I'm sorry. All right. Forget it. Forget it.
相信各位都记得那是莺鸟的呜声
And that, I'm sure you'll all remember, is the voice of the Nelles warbler.
现在看看这一位 花面伯劳
Let's turn our attention to this gentleman, the masked shrike.
又名屠夫鸟
Lanius nubicus. The butcherbird.
伯劳把敌人钉在练树丛的刺上面
The shrike impales his foes on the spikes of thorn bushes.
个性不怎么招人喜爱 看看他的色彩
Not a very lovable character, you see. Let's have a look at the coloring.
青面从头到尾是黑的
Uniform black above, from head to tail.
黑臀部 黑冠有清晰的白斑 眼睛上方有白线
A black rump, a black crown with a bold white flash, and a white line over the eye.
伯劳栖息在稀疏林地…
The shrike lives in lightly wooded country...
韩德利 请坐 桌上有绘画材料
Ah. Hendley. Sit down. You'll find drawing materials on the table.
伯劳栖息在稀疏林地 橄榄园和果园里
The shrike lives in lightly wooded country, olive groves and gardens.
韩德利 你也赏乌吗？
Well, Hendley, have you taken to birds, too, now?
是的 别走开 学点知识
Yeah. Stick around. You might learn something.
我有比画乌更重要的事可做
I have better things to do than draw birds.
呜声是单调连绩的音符 组糙又难听
The voice is a monotonous succession of scratchy, complaining notes.
仔细看看这只鸟 他有圆形的…
Now, let's have a good look at this bird. He's got a round shape...
越过边界的许可证 这里还有一张
An Urlaubsschein. Permission to cross a frontier. Here's another one.
哪一张是伪造的？
Which one's the forgery?
这张 -对
- That one. - That's right.
两张都是伪造的
They both are.
现在阻碍进度的是 新式通行证
What's holding us up now is the new form of this travel permit.
-我们不知道它们是什么样子 -这里有一张
- We've no idea what they look like. - Here's one.
还有一张军人身份证
And a military identity card.
还有…
And a...
出入证 -对
- An Ausweis. - Yeah.
-可以进入官方地点 -到奥登的火车祟
- Permission to be on Reich property. - A ticket to Oden.
似乎是祯探警卫 下星期要去的地方
What appears to be the ferret assignments for the next week.
你这次得满分了
You get ten out of ten for this, old boy.
-谢谢 小心保管 -你从哪里弄来的？
Thank you, sir. Take good care of that. - Where did you get this?
暂时借来的
It's on loan.
为了制造足够的服装
In order to get the right amount of outfits, Roger,
我建议以改造军服为主
I suggest that we work mainly from service uniforms.
我会做双排卡 单排卡
I can do double-breasteds, single-breasteds,
还有很好看的普通西装
and rather nice lounge suits.
我会做多种花样的翻领
Lapels. I can do quite a lot of things with those.
可以做得那废低 或者那么高
I can have them deep like that, or high ones like that.
我们正在做这一件
Here's one that we're working on right now.
卡子怎么办？
Oh, yes. What about buttons?
看看那些
Take a look at those.
我做好这件
Here's one that I've finished, Roger.
还有…
And, uh...
这是我用蓝墨水染的
here's one that I dyed with a bottle of blue ink.
挺好看的 罗杰 什么事？
It's rather good. What's up, Roger?
如果警卫查到这些就大丰收了
The goons'd have a field day if they crashed in on this lot.
那是索伦负责的 我已经开始利用其他材料
That's Sorren's department. Now, I've started working on the other materials.
这床毯子
This blanket.
尤其是条纹 好极了
Particularly the stripes. Marvelous.
-做外套？ -对
- Coats. - Yes.
我已经叫手下在营地各处动手
I've got the chaps working on these all over the compound.
那些战斗服 恐怕稍微短了一点
Those battle dresses, I'm afraid they're a bit too short.
我会叫手下把它们做成工人服之类
I'll have to get the chaps to make those into some sort of workingman's outfits.
毯子布套
Blanket ticking.
我把它们做成漂亮的背心
Now, I've made these into rather nice little Waistcoats.
-很师气 当然是染色的 -当然
- Very dapper, yes. Dyed, of course. - Of course.
看看这个
Just take a look at this, Roger.
我们把毯子到得很平滑
Now, this blanket material, we scrape this down until it's really smooth,
然后用鞋油染色
and then dye it with boot polish.
韩德利弄来的灯心绒 但愿有更多这种衣料
Corduroy scrounged by Hendley. I wish we had more of this.
-你从哪里弄到这些东西？ -是韩德利
- Where in God's name did you get these? - Hendley.
-他从哪里弄到的？ -我问过他
- Where did he get them? - I asked him that.
-他怎么说？ -他说“别问”
- What did he say? - "Don't ask."
给你看一些我正在做的大衣
Let me show you some of the overcoats I've been working on.
-希尔兹 早安 -早
- Good morning, Hilts. - Uh-oh.
如果你想知道我会不会再逃 我会
Well, if you're here to find out if I'm going out again, I am.
-什么时候？ -17天后 7月7日
- When? - Seventeen days, 7th of July.
-没有月光 -对
- Dark of the moon. - Correct.
艾弗斯跟你一起逃吗？
- Is Ives going with you? -
如果他要的话 可以
Yeah, if he wants to.
你知不知道艾弗斯快崩溃了？
You, uh... You know that Ives is close to cracking?
知道
Yeah.
最好让他用地道逃出去吗？ -比较安全
Better for him to go out in the tunnel, huh? - Safer.
有道理
Right.
单独行动有可能穿越铁丝网 甚至逃走
It's possible for one man to get out through the wire, even get away,
但是除了你之外 营地里还有很多人
but there are in fact a considerable number of people besides yourself
正在试图逃走
in this camp who are trying to escape.
我了解
I appreciate that.
有事情要发生了 我有感觉
Something's coming, I can feel it,
而且就要发生在我身上
and it's coming right around the corner at me, Squadron Leader.
-我的名字是罗杰 -好的 罗杰
- My name's Roger. - All right, Roger.
你叫维吉吗？
Yours is Virgil, isn't it?
希尔兹 叫我希尔兹好了
Hilts. Just make it Hilts.
好 那么…
Yes, well, um...
希尔兹 我要说的是
as I was saying, uh, Hilts,
我们有德国地图 普通的地图
we have maps of Germany, general maps, that is.
我们有逃离德国的全部资讯
We have all the information we need for the escape routes out of Germany.
但是我们没有…
But what we do not have...
树林外面五百公尺的详细情形
ls a clear idea of what's 500 yards beyond those trees.
我们试过营里每个警卫 全都失败
We've tried every goon in the camp. No go.
我们必须知道 本地城镇的确切位置
We must know the exact position of the local town.
我们想知道 在哪里连接主要道路
We want to know where we hit the main roads.
警察局在哪里 军事检查哨在哪里
Where the police stations are, where they've got their roadblocks.
最重要的是 我们必须知道如何从这里
And, most important of all, we've got to know how to get from here
去火车站
to the railway station.
绝对不行 我穿越铁丝网之后
No. Absolutely not. When I get through that wire,
绝对不会帮你们画地图
I'm not gonna be making maps for you guys.
我要远远逃走 就算他们用大炮打我 你们也听不见
I'm gonna be so far away, you won't hear if they're shooting at me with howitzers.
-可以理解 -完全理解
- Understandable. - Completely.
我乐于帮忙 但是…
I mean, I'd like to help, but...
很有趣的主意
Interesting idea.
-你要带多少人出去？ -250人
- How many you taking out? - Two hundred and fifty.
250人？
Two hundred and fifty?
是的
Yeah.
你疯了 该进疯人院 你也是
You're crazy. You too.
250人大摇大摆走在路上？
Two hundred and fifty guys just walking down the road, just like that.
有些走公路 有些格火车 还有一些走小路
Well, some on the road, some by train, some cross-country.
他们有伪造证件 服装
They'll have forged papers, clothes,
地图 罗盘 口粮
maps, compasses, rations.
想过你会引起全德国 所有警卫的注意吗？
You're gonna alert every goon in the country.
连农人都会拿着草叉来找你
Anybody that can carry a pitchfork is gonna be out looking for you.
他们会全面扫荡 很快将你们全抓起来
They're gonna swoop down and scoop you up so fast it'd make your head swim.
多谢了
Yes, well, um, thanks, anyway.
-如果地道要我帮忙 尽管说 -你真好
If I can help on the tunnel, let me know.
听候差遣
- That's good of you. - Any time.
等一下 你不是真的想我穿越铁丝网
Wait a minute. You aren't seriously suggesting that if I get through the wire
弄清楚外面的情况 躲避追捕
and case everything out there and don't get picked up,
然后回来自首关禁闭几个月
to turn myself in and get thrown back in the cooler
好让你得到需要的资料？
so you can get the information you need?
是的 我的任务 使我不得不提出奇任的要求
Yes. One has to ask some very strange things in the job I have.
-我们让你优先使用地道 -连我亲娘也别妄想
- We'll give you a front place. - I wouldn't do that for my own mother.
-我不怪你 -那么 请便
- I don't blame you. - Well, OK, then.
-我们完全谅解你 -那么 请便
- It's completely understandable. - Well, OK, then.
好吧 多谢了
Yes, well, thanks, Hilts.
将军…
Check.
韩德利 我…
- Herr Hendley, I...
不要紧 布莱斯是朋友
Oh, it's all right. Blythe's a friend.
-韦纳 什么事？ -我的皮夹 证件 身份证
What's the matter, Werner? - My wallet, my papers, my identity card.
不见了 我的东西全丢了
Gone. I lost them. Everything.
他的皮夹掉了
- He lost his wallet. - Hmm?
如果斯特赫维兹发现了 你知道会怎样吗？
Do you realize what would happen if Strachwitz found this out?
-去俄国前线 -太糟了
- The Russian front. - Dear, dear.
我找遍每个地方
I've looked every place, every place.
一定是在这里弄丢的
I must have lost them while I was in here.
不会吧 -是的
- No. - Yes.
我说过我们是朋友 我们会替你找到的
Look, I told you we were friends. We'll find them.
韩德利先生 谢谢你
Oh, thank you, Herr Hendley.
韦纳
Werner.
不是现在 如果有人看见你和我
Not now. It might look a little peculiar
这么晚探头探脑 看起来有点奇怪
if you and I were seen probing around at this time of night.
我保证会找到失物 就算折掉房子也要找到
Look, I'll find them. I promise you I'll find 'em if I have to tear this room apart.
谢谢你 -别客气
- Thank you. - Forget it.
韦纳? -什么事?
- Werner. - Yes?
请你帮个小忙
There is one small favor.
我要一架照相机
A camera.
我们想拍几张快照 当作…纪念品
We want to take some snapshots. You know... keepsakes.
35毫米镜头 2 . 8焦距和平面快门
35mm with a 2.8 lens and a plane shutter.
是焦平面快门
Focal-plane shutter.
韦纳 是焦平面快门
Werner, that's a focal-plane shutter.
弄到了就告诉我
Let me know when you got it.
韦纳是个浑小子 但是我喜欢他
He's a crazy, mixed-up kid, that Werner, but I like him.
将军
Checkmate.
鼓风机何时准备好？
How soon's our air pump going to be ready?
-明天给你 -你落后进度太多了
- I'll have it for you tomorrow. - You're badly behind schedule.
-丹尼 情况怎样？ -不好
- How's it coming, Danny? - No good.
-不好？ -今天塌了三次
- No good? - Today, three times.
威利 你还好吧？
Willie, you all right?
拉！
Pull!
你必须支撑整条地道 全部一百米都要支撑
You're gonna have to shore up the whole bloody tunnel, Roger. All 335 feet of it.
今天塌了四次
Four times today. Foom!
这样永远挖不通 我们需要更多木材
This way we never get through. We must have more wood.
需要很多木材 能弄到手吗？
It's a lot of timber, Roger. Can you get it?
会弄到的 非弄到不可
We'll get it. We've gotta get it.
我会派韩德利 和今早新加入的人去办
I'll put Hendley on it, and the new man we got this morning.
好的 威利
OK, Willie.
在圣诞的第一天 我的挚爱送给我
On the first day of Christmas my true love sent to me
一只鹧鸪和梨子树
A partridge in a pear tree
在圣诞的第二天 我的挚爱送给我
On the second day of Christmas my true love sent to me
两只斑鸠 还有一只鹧鸪和梨子树
Two turtle doves and a partridge in a pear tree
在圣诞的第四天 我的挚爱送给我
On the fourth day of Christmas my true love sent to me
四只鸣禽 三只母鸡
Four calling birds, three French hens
两只斑鸠 还有一只鹧鸪和梨子树
Two turtle doves and a partridge in a pear tree
在圣诞的第五天 我的挚爱送给我
On the fifth day of Christmas my true love sent to me
五个金戒指
Five gold rings
-上面木板的情况怎样？ -每四块抽掉一块
How's it going with the rafters up there? - Taking out one in four.
继绩进行
Stay with it.
五个金戒指
Five gold rings
四只鸣禽 三只母鸡
Four calling birds, three French hens
两只斑鸠 还有一只鹧鸪和梨子树
Two turtle doves and a partridge in a pear tree
在圣诞的第七天 我的挚爱送给我
On the seventh day of Christmas my true love sent to me
七只游泳的天鹅 六只躺着的鹅
Seven swans a-swimming, six geese a-laying
五个金戒指
Five gold rings
四只鸣禽 三只母鸡
Four calling birds, three French hens
两只斑鸠 还有一只鹧鸪和梨子树
Two turtle doves and a partridge in a pear tree
五个金戒指 四只…
I Five gold rings, four calling birds...
真难听 我从没这么辛苦过
Bloody singing. I've never worked so hard in all my life. Hi, Hilts.
卡文迪斯…
Say, Cavendish...
三只母鸡 两只斑鸠
Three French hens, two turtle doves
还有一只鹧鸪和梨子…
And a partridge in a pear...
上床！
Allez... hup!
没事
Never mind.
我们的朋友韦纳送的礼物
Here's a present from our friend, Werner.
好极了
Splendid.
实在好极了
Simply splendid.
这个应该很合用
This should do very nicely.
那是艾希利皮特的部下
Those are Ashley-Pitt's men.
他请求准许 在阁楼上堆放一些废土
He requested permission to dispose of some of his dirt in our attic.
汤姆已经挖到超过那堆木头了
Tom has reached just beyond that pile of wood, sir.
-哈利没那么远 -离树林还有多远？
Harry, of course, isn't as far as that. - How much further to the trees?
估计有15米
We make it 50 feet, sir.
-没有月光的晚上是7号… -8号和9号
- Dark of the moon is the seventh... - Eight and ninth.
8月份提早一天
A day earlier in August.
早安
Morning.
他又来了
There he goes again.
他为何要买 营地里所有的洋芋？
Why is he buying up all the potatoes in the camp?
我探听过 但是无法找到答案
I've been working on that, but I can't find out.
希尔兹与韩德利 每天晚上都混在一起
Hilts and Hendley lock themselves in every night.
地鼠有时候和他们在一起 有时在外面放哨
Sometimes Goff's with them. Other nights he's on guard outside.
麦克 我们要关闭狄克与哈利 把它们封起来
Mac, we'll close down Dick and Harry. Seal them off.
全力以赴将汤姆推进到树林里
Put the entire effort into Tom, and press on into the trees.
是的 罗杰
Right, Roger.
好
Wow.
好啊
向后转！
About face!
齐步走！
Forward march!
-这是做什么？ -他们在庆祝美国革命
- What is it? - They're celebrating the revolution.
今天是7月4号
It's the Fourth of July.
这到底是怎么回事？
What the devil's this?
我们邀请各位免费喝酒
Gentlemen, you're invited for free drinks.
美国国庆 这是殖民地的小礼物 -打倒英国人
- A little present from the colonials. - Down the British.
-说得对 为汤姆喝一杯
- Quite right, too. - And a little drink to Tom.
为回家喝一杯
- And to getting home.
很好 我们接受
Very well. We accept.
-支持叛军！ -打倒英国人！
- Up the rebels! - Down the British!
各位 请跟我们来
Gentlemen, follow us.
向后转！
About face!
立…定！
Company... halt!
在这里排队！
All right, let's line up down here!
各人拿一个杯子！
All right, grab a cup!
消卜队！开始了
Line it up! Here we go.
原来洋芋有此用处
That explains what happened to the potatoes.
汤姆停工一天不要紧
No harm in closing down Tom for one day, Roger.
轻松一下对我们都好
I suppose it'll do us all good to let off a bit of steam.
只剩下14尺了 整个营地都能感觉到
There's only 14 feet to go, sir, and you can feel it throughout the whole camp.
-我们应该喝一杯 -遵命 长官
- I think that calls for a drink. - Hear, hear.
-干杯！ -希尔兹 这是什么？
- Drink it up! - What is this stuff, Hilts?
和酒 美国和酒
Moonshine. American moonshine. Moonshine.
喝个痛快 干杯
Make my moustache grow. Cheers.
向前走
Keep it moving.
艾利克 不要洒出来
Hello, Eric. Don't spill any of that.
-给你 -打倒英国人
- There you go. - Down with the British.
好 向前移动
All right, old cobber. Keep it mo...
不要洒到衣服上 -干杯！
- Don't get any on your clothes. - Cheers!
-不要洒出来 -喝酒不嫌太早吗？
- Don't spill any of that. - Before your morning tea?
向前走
- Keep it moving.
长官 不要洒在衣服上
Don't get any on your clothes, sir.
美国和酒 酒精很多 抽烟会起火
American moonshine. Don't smoke right after you drink it.
不要抽烟 喝酒时不要抽烟
No smoking. No smoking while you're drinking.
朋友 喝个酩酊大醉
Get good and stoned, my friend.
向前走 向前…
Keep it going. Keep it...
没有国会代表权就不缴税
No taxation without representation.
小伙子 向前移动 向前…
Keep it going, boys. Keep it...
伙计们向前走 喝个痛快
Keep it going, fellas. Enjoy yourselves.
我们敬汤姆一杯
- Well, let's drink to Tom.
敬汤姆
To Tom.
我关在战俘营三年七个月 又大约两星期
In the three years, seven months and two weeks that I've been in the bag,
那是我尝过最美味的东西
that's the most extraordinary stuff I've ever tasted.
-味道真呛 -我认为还不错
- It's shattering. - Well, I think it's rather good.
长官 如果你准许的话 我去艾弗斯叫
Well, with your permission, sir, I think I'll all on kive.
我是说 去叫艾弗斯
Call on Ives.
韩德利 敬你！
Cheers, Hendley!
你知道那是什么吗？
You know what that is?
我知道这不是什么
I'll tell you what it isn't.
这不是拿破仑白兰地
It isn't Napoleon brandy.
长官 你喜欢这酒吗？
How do you like it, sir?
这个嘛…
- Well, it's, uh...
敬殖民地
To the colonies.
敬独立
Independence.
你们两人相处还好吗？
How are you managing over there without us? Getting along all right, are you?
我们相处挺融洽的 掌…长官
We seem to be getting along all right, shir... sir.
说到这个酒嘛…
Yes, well, it's, uh...
希尔兹 这是好酒
It's good stuff, Hilts.
长官 谢谢你
Thank you, sir.
丹尼！这一杯敬…
Danny! Here's to...
罗杰 警卫在105号营房
Roger, goons in 105.
-哪一个？ -斯特赫维兹
- Who? - Strachwitz.
我们必须装作若无其事 否则警卫就知道那里很重要
We have to ignore it. If we pay attention, the goons'll know the hut's important.
祝回家
Here's to going home.
丹尼 别紧张 他们搜过一百次了
Come on, Danny. They've searched it a hundred times.
回家！
Home!
很高兴你和我们合作挖地道 敬汤姆 好吗？
Anyway, I'm glad we've got you in the tunnel with us. To Tom, eh?
别担心 两星期后 你就会在亚吉尔进大街
Och, never mind. You'll be walking down Argyle Street in a couple of weeks.
敬汤姆 我现在才开始有那种感觉
To Tom. You know, Sandy, I'm just beginning to realize that myself.
当然应该有那种感觉 我们几乎要到树林了
Why shouldn't you, man? We're nearly at the trees, boy.
我们几乎要到树林了 是吗？
We're nearly at the trees, eh?
士官长！
Herr Hauptfeldwebel! Herr Hauptfeldwebel!
就这样
Das ist es also.
去守着！
Los, holen Sie die Wache!
我猜对了
Ich hab's doch geahnt.
老天！他们发现汤姆了
Oh, my God! They've found Tom.
地道被发现了
It's the tunnel.
成功个鬼
Success.
艾弗斯！
Ives!
不许动！
Halt!
长官 请告诉我 你需要什么资料
Sir, let me know the exact information you need.
-我今晚逃出去 -好的
- I'm going out tonight. - Right.
打开 哈利
Open up, Harry.
我们一天24小时挖掘
We dig. Around the clock.
禁闭室 关就关
- Cooler. - Right.
没想到他们这么快抓到他
Well, I didn't think they'd catch him so soon.
他不是被抓到的
He wasn't caught.
希尔兹 欢迎回家
Hilts, welcome home.
丹尼？
Danny?
丹尼 你没事吧？
Are you all right, Danny?
没事
Yes.
我没事
All right.
拿铲子来 我没事
All right. Bring some shovels. I'm all right.
老天爷 你满掉了整个飞鹰标志
For God's sake, you've left out a whole eagle.
那不可能
That's impossible.
是满掉了
Yes.
四天的辛苦白费了！
Four days' work up the bloody spout!
柯林 对不起
- I'm sorry, Colin. -
史密斯 不要紧
It's all right, Smithy.
已经很晚了 你去睡吧 我来收拾这里
It's getting late. You push off to bed. I'll pack up here.
是的
All right.
-柯林 晚安 -史密斯 晚安
- Good night, Colin. - Good night, Smithy.
我什么都看不见
I can't see a bloody thing.
脱帽
Hut ab.
很好 就这样 谢谢
Sehr gut. In Ordnung. Danke schön.
请进
- Bitte schön. - Herein.
希特勒万岁
Heil Hitler.
-你叫什么名字 -埃里希·斯崔尔 来自慕尼黑
- Wie heißen Sie? - Erich Stressel, aus München.
你怎么在这里
Warum sind Sie hier?
我请假了 我母亲生病了
Ich habe Urlaub bekommen. Meine Mutter ist krank.
-你的德语很好 -谢谢 我花了很多…
- Your German's very good. - Thanks, Mac. I've put in a lot of...
注意！那是最容易的一招 不要被那个老套招式骗到
Watch it. That's the easiest way to trip up a suspect. Don't fall for that old gag.
-对不起 -记住永远说德语
- I'm sorry, Mac. - OK. But remember, German always.
这里
Herein.
1 2 3 4 5
One, two, three, four, five.
罗杰
Roger.
不是 是我
No, it's me.
你喜不喜欢这套逃亡装？
How do you like the old escape suit?
很好
Fine, fine.
柯林
Colin.
你喜欢我的吗？
How do you like mine?
看起来好极了
It looks splendid.
丹尼 你要去哪里？ 你会被枪毙的
Where are you going? You'll get yourself shot.
-怎么回事？ -我要从铁丝网出去
- What's the matter with you? - I'm going out through that fence.
丹尼 我们从地道出去 我就要出发了
Danny, we're getting out through the tunnel. We're almost clear.
威利 别管我
Please, Willie, let me alone.
我无法再进那个地道
I can't go in that tunnel anymore.
我要从铁丝网出去
So I'm going out through the wire.
丹尼 想清楚 我们要出去 但不是从铁丝网
Danny, think. We're getting out, but not through the wire.
我们要从地道出去 地道已经完工了
We're getting out through the tunnel. It's finished.
-我现在就出去 -不要
- I go out now. - No.
丹尼 你从铁丝网出去 会被射杀
Danny, you go through that wire and you'll get killed.
不要那样
Don't do that.
威利…
Willie...
从我小时候
Since I was a boy,
我就讨厌…而且害怕小房间
I hate... and feared little rooms,
橱柜 山洞
closets, caves.
丹尼 你挖过17条地道 不只17条地道
Danny, you've dug 17 tunnels. Over 17 tunnels.
我必须逃出去
Because I must get out.
我藏起恐惧 努力挖掘
I hide the fear, and I dig.
但是明天晚上在地道里 有这么多人
But tomorrow night in the tunnel with all those men,
我怕这次会丧失理智
I'm afraid maybe this time I will lose my head,
毁了大家的计划
and ruin the escape for everybody.
所以我现在就逃
So I go now.
丹尼 我会照顾你穿过地道
Danny, I'll see you through the tunnel.
我会照顾你 我会一路跟着你
I'll look after you. I'll stick with you all the way.
好吧
All right.
-晚安 -哈啰 罗杰
- Good evening. - Hello, Roger.
你认为我们看起来怎样？
Well, how do you think we look?
先生 晚上好 您好吗
Guten Abend, mein Herr. Wie geht es Ihnen?
你认为我们看起来怎样？
Well, how do you think we look?
先生 晚上好 您好吗
Guten Abend, mein Herr. Wie geht es Ihnen?
我德语那么糟吗？
It's as bad as all that?
柯林 我首先要说如果没有你 我们就不能准备好
Colin, I want first of all to say that without you, we would not have been ready.
别客气 我有很多帮手 很多很好的帮手
That's all right. I had lots of help. Lots of very good help.
罗杰 什么事？
What's the matter, Roger?
你不能参加逃脱
You can't go.
-你是什么意思？ -我不能让你出去
- What do you mean? - I can't allow it.
-为什么？ 你连眼前的手都看不见
Why? You can't see your hand in front of your face.
你逃不出十公尺就会被抓到
You'd be caught before you got 10 yards.
那太可笑了
That's ridiculous.
那太可笑了 我从没听过这么荒谬的事
That's ridiculous. Never heard anything so absurd in my life.
我视力没问题
I can see perfectly. I can see perfectly!
我能够看见…那边那根针
I can see... that pin down there.
-你满意了吗？ 什么针？在哪里？
- Does that satisfy you? - What pin? Where?
柯林 你看见门槛吗？
Colin, do you see the foot of the door?
当然看见了
Yes, of course.
把这根针放在那里 好吗？
Put the pin down there, will you?
可以
All right.
没事了 过来
All right. Come on.
过来 坐下
Come on. Sit down.
坐下 你努力试过了
Sit down. It was a good try.
我不想最后一刻让你失望 但是有人告诉我
I hate these last-minute letdowns, but I've only just been told.
-太冒险了 -你不认为要让柯林来决定吗？
It's too risky for you. - Don't you think that's Colin's decision?
-我不认为 -罗杰 别这样
- No, I don't. - Come on, Roger.
我们都知道是怎么回事 至少…大部份人知道
We all know the score here. Well, at least... most of us do.
这次逃脱的构想 是开辟另一条战线
Your idea of this escape is to start another front,
在防线后方扰乱德国人 没关系 那样很好
to foul up the Germans behind the lines. All right, that's fine.
但是只要我们越过铁丝网 迫使他们到处寻找我们
But once we get past that wire and have them looking all over Germany for us,
任务就完成了
that mission is accomplished.
完成任务之后 我们有自己的想法
Afterwards, we have some ideas of our own.
你是说回家？
You mean getting home?
回到家人身边？ -对
- Back to your family? - That's right.
你真的以为我不想回家吗？
Do you really believe I haven't thought about that, too?
我相信你想
I'm sure you have.
我知道柯林想
I know Colin has.
我也想
And, Roger, I have, too.
我们认为能够一路逃回去
We think we can make it all the way.
柯林不能 他会严重危害整个计划 必须由我来决定
Not Colin. He'd be an appalling hazard to the escape. That must be my decision.
让我们来谈谈危害 先谈谈你
Let's talk about hazard. Let's talk about you.
你是我们最大的危害 秘密警察已经锁定你了
You're the biggest hazard we have. The Gestapo has you marked.
但是没人说你不可以逃
No one has said you can't go.
你说的对
That's true.
我已经考虑到秘密警察
I have thought about the Gestapo.
但是如果你问我 -个指挥官可以做或者胆敢做
But if you're asking me how far a commanding officer is allowed to go,
多大的冒险
or dare go,
或者他可不可以纷演上帝？
or should be permitted to play God,
我无法回答你
I can't answer you.
但是我能够告诉你
But I can tell you
盲人对于自己和整个计划 都是不必要的危害
a blind man is an unnecessary hazard to himself and the whole plan,
必须排除在逃亡计划之外
and must therefore be eliminated from the operation.
柯林和我一起就不是盲人 他会和我一起
Colin's not a blind man as long as he's with me, and he's going with me.
柯林 你愿意吗？
It's all right with you, Colin?
很愿意
Oh, yes. Quite.
很好 我会安排你和柯林一起逃脱
Very well. I'll arrange for your escape numbers to be altered accordingly.
俩位 晚安
Good night, gentlemen.
其实…
Actually...
他说的很对
he's quite right.
他说的完全正确
He's completely right.
我真的不应该逃
I really shouldn't go at all.
我的视力最近愈来愈差
My eyes have been getting worse and worse lately.
这好像叫作恶性近视
I think they call it progressive myopia.
我能看见这么近的东西
I can see things up here. Close to.
我能够用眼力工作 但是…
I can see to work, but, uh...
看你只是一团模糊
- you're just a blur.
我知道
I know.
管它的 我们会很顺利的
Oh, hell. We'll make it in great shape.
柯林 你有茶吗？
Colin, do you have any tea?
-当然有 -我们喝一点
- Yes, of course. - Then let's have some.
好极了
Splendid.
出去
Raus.
希尔兹
- Hi, Hilts.
麦克
Hey, Mac.
什么时候？
When?
今天晚上 以为他们永远不放你出来
Tonight. We thought they'd never let you out.
我也以为是 我们谈正事吧
Me, too. Let's get at it.
巴特利在等你 -我会到的
- Bartlett's waiting for you. - I'll be there.
现在什么时间？
What time?
丹尼 只剩八分钟了
Only eight minutes now, Danny.
你没事吧？
You OK?
卡文迪斯
Cavendish.
葛里夫 去那边
Griff, down there.
戈福 去那边
Goff, there.
史密斯 福尔斯 右边第三床
Smith, Foles, third on the right.
布莱斯 韩德利 左边第三床
Blythe, Hendley, third on the left.
灯亮了
There are the lights.
丹尼 分秒不差
Right on the tick, Danny.
丹尼 顺着地道看 它真美
Look down the tunnel, Danny. It's lovely.
像是旅游旺季的黑潭海滨
It's just like Blackpool at the height of the season.
丹尼 你去过黑潭吗？
You ever been to Blackpool, Danny?
去过
Yes.
没去过
No.
我不知道
I don't know.
罗杰 时间到了
It's time, Roger.
巴特利 麦居纳 艾希利皮特
Bartlett, MacDonald, Ashley-Pitt.
长官 可以走了
It's all clear, sir.
罗杰 全准备好了
All set, Roger.
罗杰
Roger.
祝好运
Good luck.
丹尼 他们正从竖坑下来
They're coming down the shaft now, Danny.
然后他们会顺着地道过来
And then they'll be coming right up the tunnel.
威利…
Willie...
我不能等了 我必须出去
I can't wait. I must get out.
丹尼！丹尼！
Danny! Danny! Danny! Danny!
丹尼 什么事？ 丹尼！过来！
What is it, Danny? What's the matter? Danny! Come here!
罗杰 丹尼和我等一下才走 我们消卜后一点
Roger? Danny and I'll go later. We'll take another place.
丹尼 告诉我怎么回事 快点！
Danny, tell me what this is, and tell me quickly!
这地道是大家的也是我的 我挖的 我造的
This tunnel is mine as much as anybody. I dug it. I built it.
我被埋过很多次 我想走就走
I was buried many times. I go when I want.
让我出去 让我出去
Let me out. Let me out.
威利 带他出去
Take him out, Willie. Take him out.
丹尼？怎么回事？
Danny? What is it?
丹尼 出了什么事？
Danny, what's going on?
塞奇威克 没事 我们等一会再走
It's all right, Sedgwick. It's all right. We're going later.
丹尼 没事的
Danny, it's all right. It's all right.
我们可以排后一点 没事的
We can take another place in the line. It's all right.
柯林 该你下去
All right, Colin. Down you go.
坐下用右脚找梯子的第一级 找到了吗？
Sit down. Feel the top rung of the ladder with your right foot. Got it?
向下爬
Down you go.
丹尼退出吗？
Danny cut out, huh?
威利带他上去 希尔兹 我…
Willie took him up top. Hilts, I, uh...
-记住 别挂头 -好的
- Remember, keep your head down. - Right.
巴勒特
Psst. Bartlett.
如何
All right?
-慢慢来 糟了 差了6公尺 -是什么意思？
Hold onto yourself. You're 20 feet short. - What do you mean?
差6公尺才到树林 地道出口在空地上
Twenty feet short of the woods. The hole is in the open.
警卫在我们和探照灯之间
The guard is between us and the lights.
怎么会这样？
How could that happen?
现在争论也没意思 生米已经煮成熟饭
What the hell difference does it make? It's happened.
-罗杰… -别吵 我要想一想！
- Roger... - Damn it, Mac! I'm trying to think!
我们可以延期 挖到树林
We could postpone it.
所有文件日期都是今天 时机一去不回
All the documents are dated today. It's now or never.
只有一个机会 趁警卫走到那边时逃出去
One chance. When the guard goes to the far end, you might be able to move out.
我能跑进树林用信号通知你们
I think I can make it to the woods, set up a signal when you're clear.
瞭望塔怎么办？
What about the towers?
必须冒险 他们监看的是营地 不是树林
They're gonna be watching the compound, not the woods.
麦克 传话下去 送十公尺的绳子过来
Mac, pass the word. Send down 30 feet of rope.
送十公尺的绳子过来！
Send down 30 feet of rope!
送十公尺的绳子过来
Send down 30 feet of rope.
送十公尺的绳子过来！
Send down 30 feet of rope!
-什么？ -十公尺的绳子！
- What? - Thirty feet of rope!
-要绳子做什么？ -我怎么知道？快拿绳子来
- What do they want that for? - How should I know? Get the rope.
-情况怎样？听说了吗？ -长官 我猜是出了麻烦
- How's it going? Have you heard? - Some kind of foul-up, I think, sir.
-他们还没进入地道吗？ -长官 还没有
Haven't they moved into the tunnel yet? - I don't think so, sir.
他进树林了
He's over there.
好 艾利克 你先上
Right. You go first, Eric.
我在这里等到一切顺利进行
I'm staying here till we get moving.
毕卡第利大街见 -史考特酒吧
- See you in Piccadilly. - Scott's Bar.
好
Right.
谢谢你
Thank you.
-祝好运 -好的
- Good luck. - Right.
该我们了
We're moving.
丹尼 他们在通过地道 他们正在逃出去
Danny, they're moving through the tunnel now. They're getting out.
华沙沦陷时 你是飞行员 逃到英国
When Warsaw fell, you escaped and came to England because you're a flier.
你逃过来是想与我们一起 在天空对德军战斗
You came because you wanted to fly with us and fight the Germans.
我们现在能够逃出去 可以回到英国
We can get out now. We can get back to England.
如果你不从地道逃走
If you don't go through that tunnel,
你做过的每一件事都会变成无意义！
everything you've done will have been for nothing, nothing!
-麦克 布莱斯在后面 -知道了
- Blythe's behind, Mac. - Right.
柯林 来这里
- In here, Colin. - Come on.
坐下
Sit down.
塞奇威克 该你了 我来接手
You're up, Sedgwick. I'll take over.
里面装了什么？钢琴吗？ -你真会说笑
- What have you got in here? A piano? - That's very funny, mate.
-这东西过不了地道 -我自有办法
- You won't get this thing through. - I'll cope.
塞奇威克和他的箱子吗？ -还会是谁
- Was that Sedgwick with his trunk? - Who else?
真希望他留在澳洲陪袋鼠
I wish he was home with his kangaroos.
-地道短了6公尺 -什么鬼…？
- We're 20 feet short. - How the hell...?
短了6公尺 希尔兹在树林里 控制绳子的另一端
Hilts is on the other end of that rope in the woods.
感觉绳子拉两下时就出去 让柯林趴下
As soon as you feel a couple of tugs, off you go, but keep Colin low.
-柯林 祝好运 -麦克 多谢
- Good luck, Colin. - Thanks, Mac.
那是什么声音？
What's that?
-是空袭 天哪！不要！
- It's an air raid. - Oh, God! No!
警卫会关拌电源 地道就没有灯光了
The goons'll pull the switches. We'll lose the lights in the tunnel.
柯林 来吧 趁熄灯的时候出去
Come on, Colin. We can get out when the lights go down.
威利
Willie.
威利！
Willie!
是空袭 探照灯关了 赶快！
It's an air raid. Searchlights are out. Come on!
叫他们出去
Get 'em out.
-地道要塌了！ -丹尼
- It's gonna give! - Danny.
丹尼 没事的 丹尼 是灯熄了
Danny. Danny, it's all right. Danny, it's the lights.
点燃底下的油灯！
Light the lamps down there!
是空袭 他们熄了灯
There's been an air raid and they've cut the lights.
丹尼 听我说 地道没事的！
Danny, it's all right. Listen to me!
丹尼 你看
Danny, look.
伙计们 快点啊！ 可以趁黑逃走几十人
Come on, fellas. Move! Move! We can get dozens out in this darkness.
究竟怎么回事？
What the hell's going on?
-你走 -丹尼 不要
- You go. - No. Danny.
走啊
Go.
-威利 什么事？ -是丹尼
- What is this, Willie? - Danny.
-他卡在里面吗？ -他没事
- Is he stuck in there? - He's all right.
叫他赶快出来！
Get him out fast.
快点
Psst. Come on.
丹尼 快点 前进
Come on, Danny, move.
你快跑
Up you go-.
袋子给我
Give me your bag.
我们等绳子信号！
We're on the rope!
你和我最好出去 否则没机会赶上任何火车
You and I had better get out, or we won't have a chance of any of the trains.
进展顺利 我们只要交待指示就行了
It's moving. We'll just have to pass the instructions from man to man.
-好的 -我在你后面
- Right. - I'll be right behind you.
有人吗
Ist da jemand?
-有回应吗 -没有
- Hast du etwas gehört'? - Nein.
快拉啊 快拉啊
Come on, come on.
快拉啊
Come on.
不要开枪！
- Hey! - Don't shoot!
Don't shoot!
不要开枪！
快让开！我们要回来！
Get off! We're coming back!
老天 上面枪声热闹极了
Oh, boy. There's a hell of a lot of shooting going on up there.
德军在他们爬出去时开枪吗？
Think they've been shooting them as they came out?
不是 否则我们早听到枪声了
We would've heard the shots before.
等等我
- Pull! - Wait for me.
出来
Out.
出去
清点完毕 长官
Die Aufstellung, Herr Hauptmann.
-76人 -是的
- Sechsundsiebzig. - Jawohl.
-他说逃走多少？ -76人
- How many did he say? - Seventy-six.
解散
- Dismissed. - Ten hut!
没赶上火车的人 有一半都挤在这里
Half the guys who missed their trains are piled up here.
艾希利皮特 罗杰 麦居纳 尼莫
Ashley-Pitt, Roger, MacDonald, Nimmo.
真是一大群人
Makes quite a group.
-我们怎么办？ -等火车
- What do we do? - Wait for the train.
谢谢
Merci.
带上我吧
Können Sie mich mitnehmen?
可以 上车
Aber gerne. Steigen Sie ein.
非常感谢
Danke schön.
护照
Ihre Pässe, bitte.
有情况
Tallyho.
你是法国人吗 - 是的
- Vous êtes Français? - Oui.
我也是
Moi, aussi.
谢谢
- Merci bien. - Merci.
有情况
Tallyho.
您是要出公差吗 -是的
- Sie reisen für eine Firma? - Ja.
谈生意
Fur mein Geschäft.
谢谢
- Danke. - Danke.
-警察在火车上吗？ -还有秘密警察 我们跳车
- Are the police on the train? - The Gestapo are with them. Let's jump.
-我告诉你何时跳 -我宁愿你猛推我一把
I'll tell you when. I'd prefer you just to give me a firm push.
-你没事吧？ -我没事
- Are you all right? - Yes, I'm fine.
真刺激
That's quite exciting.
-火车没有停下来 -没有 我们没被看到
- It isn't stopping. - No, we're all right.
瑞士
Switzerland.
你去哪里？回来
Wo willst du hin? Komm mal her.
你去哪里？出示证件
Wo willst du denn hin? Zeig mal deinen Ausweis.
巴特利
Bartlett.
所有人趴在地上
Alles auf den Boden.
-卡文迪斯 你要去哪里？ -我…我还没决定
- Where were you going, Cavendish? - I, uh... I hadn't quite decided.
你在路上搜集什么资料？
What information were you to collect on the way?
没有
None.
你收到什么破坏指令？
What sabotage directions did you receive?
你利用文件做了什么事？
What have you done with your papers?
-什么文件？ -伪造的文件和身份证
- Papers? - Forged papers and identity cards.
不要装傻 你利用文件做什么？
Don't be so stupid. What did you do with them?
我只是从战俘营逃出来
All I did was escape from a prison camp.
如果你被关了三年 你也会逃的
You'd do the same if you'd been locked up for three years.
-我想回家 -你无法与妻儿重众
I wanted to get home. - I don't think you'll see your wife again.
你们抓错人了 我还没结婚
You've got the wrong man. I'm not even married.
你穿的是平民服装
You're wearing civilian clothes.
你是间谍 间谍应该被枪毙
You're a spy. Spies are being shot.
这是我的军服 我瘦了 所以改小
This is my uniform. I had to recut it when I lost weight.
我用鞋油染色来遮住
I dyed it with boot polish to cover some oil smears
我被击落时沾到的油污
I picked up when I was shot down.
你的军阶符号也磨掉了？
And you lost your insignia over the years?
没错
That's right.
带走他
Bringen Sie ihn zu den anderen.
-听我说… -卡文迪斯 没别的事了
- Look... - That's all, Cavendish.
弟兄们
Hello, boys.
哈啰 大卫
Hello.
-哈啰 海因斯 -哈啰 卡文迪斯
- Hello, Haynes. - Hello, Cavendish.
我但愿能说很高兴看见你
I wish I could say I was happy to see you again.
-刚被抓到？ -今天早上
- Just picked up? - Yes, this morning.
那里有一架我会开的教练机
There's a trainer out there I can fly.
-有卫兵吗？ -有 这是个问题
- Any sentries? - Yeah, it's gonna be a problem.
柯林 我说“转”时 就顺时钟方向转这个
Colin, when I say go, crank this clockwise.
发动机起动后 不要动 否则你就会投上螺旋浆
When the engine catches, don't move, or you'll get a mouth full of propeller.
下一站 就是瑞士！
Next stop, Switzerland!
阿尔卑斯山
- The Alps.
太好了
Splendid.
过了这座山 再飞20分钟 我们就成功了
Over this range, then 20 more minutes and we've got it made.
-什么问题？没汽油吗？ -我不知道 有油但是没动力
- What is it? Petrol? - I don't know. We're losing power.
往那边走！我会跟上来
Go that way! I'll follow.
韩德利
Hendley?
柯林！
Colin!
不要！不要开枪！
Stop! Don't shoot! Please!
柯林…对不起 我弄砸了
Colin... I'm sorry I fouled things up.
没关系
That's all right.
谢谢你…
Thank you for...
带我…出来
getting me... out.
快点起来
Los, aufstehen.
举起手来
Hände hoch.
大家好 你好吗 你好吗
Bonjour, messieurs. Comment ça va? Ça va bien?
大家好
Bonjour.
像往常一样 三杯茴香酒 对不对？
Comme d'habitude, trois Pernod, n'est-ce pas?
爸爸 三个茴香酒
Trois Pernod, Papa.
这里是苏珊酒馆
Café Suzette.
是的
Oui.
-来了 先生们 三杯茴香酒 -谢谢
- Et voilà, messieurs, les trois Pernod. - Merci.
两杯
Deux...
三杯 还有水
Et trois. Et voilà de l'eau.
-用餐愉快 先生们  -谢谢
- Bon appétit, messieurs. - Merci.
先生 你的电话
Monsieur. Téléphone pour vous.
-我的电话？ -是的先生 电话
- Téléphone pour moi? - Oui, monsieur, téléphone.
在这边
Par ici.
这儿 电话
Voila', téléphone.
谢谢
Merci.
喂
Hello?
敬反抗军
Resistance.
反抗军？
Resistance?
你是英格兰人？
You are English?
我是澳洲人
I'm Australian.
你可以说英语 我听得懂
- Dites-moi... - You can speak English. I understand.
好极了 我是英军军官
Bloody good. I'm a British officer.
刚从德国的战俘营逃出来
I've just escaped from a prisoner-of-war camp in Germany.
我正在试图前往西班牙 你明白吗？
I'm trying to make my way into Spain. You understand me?
你能帮我吗？
- Oui. - Can you help me?
-我知道有人能帮你 -好极了
- I know someone who can. - Bloody good.
德国秘密警察 请出示证件
Geheime Staatspolizei. Ihren Ausweis, bitte.
啊 法国人？-是的
- Ah, Français? - Jawohl.
-商人？ -是的 你会说法语吗
- Commerçant? - Mais oui. Parlez-vous français?
-会一点 -你的发音不错
- Un peu. - Votre accent est trés bon.
我在高中学的
Je l'ai étudié dans l'école supérieure.
很好 走吧
Trés bien. Passez.
再见 先生 再见
Au revoir, monsieur. Au revoir.
祝好运 -谢谢你
- Good luck. - Thank you.
站住
Halt!
集合两个营 英国人
Zwei vom Lager sind getürmt. Engländer.
快
Los!
都上车
Alles einsteigen.
上车
Einsteigen.
站住
Halt! Halt!
不许动！ 举起手来
Stehen bleiben! Hände hoch!
干什么 -你是英国人
- Was soll das? - You are English.
英国人？
Engländer?
你用枪威胁我？
Sie drohen mir mit einer Pistole?
-带他们走 -哦 你是德国人吗？
- Nehmen Sie die weg. - Ach, Sie sind Deutscher?
-当然了 -好吧 不好意思
- Selbstverständlich. - Schon gut. Entschuldigung.
巴特利先生？
Herr Bartlett?
我叫弗洛里希
IIch heiße Frölich.
你的德语很好
Your German is good.
听说你的法语也不错
And I hear also your French.
举手！
Your arms... up!
非常好
Ausgezeichnet!
巴特利先生…
Herr Bartlett...
还有麦居纳先生
and Herr MacDonald.
我们又见面了
We are together again.
你会后悔给我们找这么多麻烦
You are going to wish you had never put us to so much trouble.
-罗杰 烦恼什么？ -我只是有一点意外
- What's troubling you, Roger? - I'm just a little surprised.
我认为要不是审问很久 就是很短的旅程
I expected either a long stay or a very short trip.
原来如此
Yes.
我必须承认有一点担忧
I have to admit, I'm a little worried, though.
我祈求上帝 我没有害了七十多个人
I hope to God I haven't blotted 70-odd ledgers.
别担心
Och, no, no.
我们全都已经成年 行动自由而且无牵无挂
We're all over 21, footloose and fancy-free.
要是没有你 我们不可能逃这么远
We'd never have got as far as we did without you, Roger.
我认为你表现出色
For what it's worth, I think you did a damn good job.
-我们都表现非常出色 -对啊
- I think we all do. - Yes.
发生什么了 我们在哪
Was ist los? Wo sind wir?
你们现在可以下车 舒展筋骨五分钟
All right. You can get out now. Stretch your legs for five minutes.
还要好几小时才抵达战俘营
It will take hours before you reach the camp.
这一切 逃亡组织 地道 汤姆与哈利
You know, Mac, all this, the organization, tunneling, Tom and Harry,
让我活得有意义
kept me alive.
虽然我们…
And even though we...
但是我从来没这么高兴过
I've never been happier.
麦克…
You know, Mac...
11位你的部下今天被送回来
Eleven of your men are being returned today.
是哪些人？
- Oh, who? -
我没有相关的资料
I do not have that information.
我
I...
上级让我通知你…
I am directed by a higher authority to inform you that...
你麾下的50位军官 在脱逃时遭到枪击
50 of your officers were shot while escaping.
枪击？
Shot?
他们的…个人物品会送回这里
Their... personal effects will be returned.
其中有多少人受伤？
How many of them were wounded?
这张名单是…死者
Here are the names... of the dead.
50人中有多少人受伤？
How many of the 50 were wounded?
半个也没有
None.
上级他们
They, the higher authority...
只让我通知你…
only directs me to inform you that...
50人被…
that 50 men were...
我明白了
I see.
约翰艾迪生
Addison, John.
彼德艾拉岱尔
Alladale, Peter.
爱德华班克罗夫特
Bancroft, Edward.
罗杰巴特利
Bartlett, Roger.
丹尼斯卡文迪斯
Cavendish, Dennis.
大卫艾德利
Eldridge, David.
威廉费尔顿
Felton, William.
亚瑟方萧
Fanshaw, Arthur.
在这里吗 -是的长官
- Ici? - Oui, monsieur.
好 再见
Alors, au revoir.
-非常感谢您 先生 -没什么 再见
- Merci beaucoup, monsieur. - Pas de quoi. Au revoir.
再见 -祝你好运
- Au revoir. - Bonne chance.
先生 我是你的向导
I am your guide, sefior.
西班牙？
For Spain?
西班牙
EspaÑa.
-真高兴看到你们都平安 -长官 谢谢你
- Glad to see you're all safe. - Thank you, sir.
多少人被抓回来？ -你们是第一批
- How many have been brought back? - You're the first.
-你知道多少人逃成了吗？ -还不知道
- Do you know how many got away? - Not yet.
布莱斯呢？
What happened to Blythe?
长官 他没成功
He didn't make it, sir.
罗杰说的对
Roger was right about that.
恐怕罗杰也没成功
I'm afraid Roger didn't make it, either.
我刚贴出名单 他们枪杀…50人
I've just posted the list. They shot... 50.
秘密警察谋杀了他们
The Gestapo murdered them.
50人？
Fifty?
麦居纳 艾希利皮特？
MacDonald, Ashley-Pitt?
死了
- Yes.
丹尼和威利？
Danny and Willie?
没有 他们不在名单上
No, they're not on the list.
海因斯？ -死了
- Haynes? - Yes.
我很难过
I'm sorry.
罗杰的构想是尽可能还击敌人
Roger's idea was to get back at the enemy the hardest way he could.
扰乱敌人的运作
Mess up the works.
从我们听到的消息 我认为他完全做到了
From what we've heard here, I think he did exactly that.
你认为值得吗？
Do you think it was worth the price?
那要看你的观点而定
That depends on your point of view, Hendley.
是的 长官
Yes, sir.
立正
Achtung!
不要向他敬礼 他已经不是指挥官了
He is not to be saluted. He's no longer in command.
工作不顺利 是吗？
The job just didn't work out, huh?
-希尔兹 你很幸运 -幸运？因为我没有…
- You were lucky, Hilts. - Lucky? Because I didn't...
多少人？
How many?
50人
Fifty.
看起来好像你会比我先看见柏林
It looks, after all, as if you will see Berlin before I do.
长官
Sir.
希尔兹 接住！
Hey, Hilts!
本片献给丧生的50人
剧终
R3官中OCR：darylhsu
校对&后期：BryanT